Rafael Cassemiro Freire

rafaelcfreire@gmail.com | www.rafaelcfreire.github.io | Contagem -MG

Summary

I have been working with software development for about 7 years. During this time I have had the opportunity to work in projects of different sizes, scope and goals, most of the time been an adopter of JEE architecture and related implementations being focused on Spring framework solutions (MVC, DI), I have a solid knowledge in Web Development tools like Sass, HTML5, CSS3 and a variety of JavaScript libraries. Currently I am studying functional approach, which is helping me toward achieve high quality code and define concise patterns of coding. I am a very enthusiastic in topics related with metrics of quality in code and usually write about it in my personal blog where I describe some of my experience in software development. My main objective in career nowadays is to work and contribute with definitions in a company where code quality is essential and practiced in everyday tasks, not just a buzzword.

Education

INSTITUTO DE GESTAO DE TECNOLOGIA DA INFORMAÇÃO

PostGraduation Lato Sensu in Software Architecture Strategies

UNIVERSITY PUC MINAS

Bachelor of Information Systems 2004-2009

Certifications

- IBM Certified Solution Designer Object Oriented Analysis and Design, vUML 2.
- IBM Certified Solution Designer IBM Rational Unified Process v7.0
- Oracle Certified Professional Java SE Programmer 82% achievement
- ETS TOEIC

Work Experience

MANUSCRIPT REVIEWER (NON PAID VOLUNTARY WORK)| MANNING PUBLICATIONS | CURRENTLY

• I am working as a manuscript reviewer in new publishings of Manning Publications. This is a specific review before the book being released, I am responsible for reading the text, execute the code examples and find errors and possible points of misunderstanding. Currently I am working in "Functional Reactive Programming in Action" to be released in 2015.

SYSTEM ANALYST | UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DE MINAS GERAIS | CURRENTLY - 05/2013

 I develop a Java EE system for the public healthcare in Brazil. This system is responsible for measurement of taxes and budget for states according to its demand. Furthermore, this application is a Web transactional system, using JSF 2.0 and Richfaces for the UI. Spring framework as transactional controller and Hibernate as ORM. I work directly with definitions of code quality patterns and Sonar to ensure our level of coding.

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER | AVENUE CODE LLC | 08/2011 - 05/2013

I worked as a backend developer for the cliente Macys. It was a Product Information System using Spring MVC as main framework for view and Controller layers and Hibernate as repository layer, in

this project we strongly used TDD during creation of new stories. Another relevant contribution I made was in a media integration for the macys.com that was planned for users world wide. The tech stack was Facebook API focused in Javascript and JQuery.

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER | ALGAR TECNOLOGIA/SYNOS TECHNOLOGIES | 09/2009 - 08/2011

Development of a system focused in control taxes for the Minas Gerais government. Using JEE5 platform with a proprietary framework called Unifw that mainly is a abstraction layer for EJB2.1 avoiding some of his workarounds and need for configuration files. In this project I was responsible for refactoring the core of the application that consists in heavy use of remote transactions which improved the performance in 50 per cent in terms of memory usage and minimized in 30% the complexity of the code.

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER | ADI SISTEMAS DE INFORMACAO | 09/2009 - 02/2008

Development of a ERP focused in city hall's management. Based in a unified process and using the JEE5 spec mainly. The architecture is based on a three tier app with JSP, JavaBeans and JDBC, integration with third part software using SOAP(XML). Acted as tech leader in a specific module related with financial limits.

Portfolio

- Rafael Freire Tech Blog http://rafaelcfreire.github.io
- LinkedIn Profile https://www.linkedin.com/in/rafaelcfreire
- GitHub Profile https://github.com/rafaelcfreire
- BitBucket Profile https://bitbucket.org/rafaelcfreire
- CodePen page http://codepen.io/rafaelcfreire
- Article "Favorecendo a qualidade de código com analise estática" published in Java Magazine 109

http://www.devmedia.com.br/codificando-com-selo-de-qualidade-revista-java-magazine-109/26309